[Music]
hello what is up my friends great to be
back with you
i hope you're doing well
and today is the 44th live episode of
ask a budget today i am taking your live
chat questions
all the questions i will be taking live
only
so let me see who all is there i can say
divesh guru simmer singh lone wolf the
alien rishabh
harshit
kapil
black widow abhishek kumar aryan
chakravarti picks arts kiran satoru
dk boss kira
megna saurabh and so many more people
great to be with you all
thank you for being here i really
appreciate your viewership i appreciate
all your support very much thank you so
much
so what shall we discuss today shall we
discuss history shall we discuss science
physics
culture religion what shall we discuss i
will take your questions you guys decide
what we discussed today
so let me see do you have questions
start asking me right now
let me see do you all have any questions
what questions do you have
let us start by this question by kira
kira says
[Laughter]
why do you hate nehru so much i know he
was selected not elected first as pm
and he did some blunders little some
small blood nurse in the 1962 war and
then kashmir etc
but he also did some great great things
like the establishment of the iim and
iit et cetera
so why do you hate mr nehru so much who
says i hate mr nehru i am an
enormous fan
of our great prime minister shri
jawaharlal nehru i think he is the most
towering prime minister we have ever had
in this country the greatest of all time
i mean look at the contributions he has
done to the country
his contributions in kashmir his
contributions in the northeast of india
the kabu valley the cocoa islands
the gwadar port the
indus
rivers treaty
uh
aksai chin
i mean
uh the the
what's article 370 i mean you one runs
out of
of ways to praise sri jawaharlal nehru
that's how great he was
who says
who says i hate him i mean yeah he did
some very small tiny little blunders
that we should just forget about
it so what if he gave away half of
kashmir so what if he gave away tibet so
what if he gave away excite chin so what
if he gave away the guadalupe so what if
he refused to make india the permanent
member of the security council so what
if he refused american offers of nuclear
weapons technology transfer so what if
he gave with the cabo valley to burma so
what if he gave away cocoa islands
so what if he
prevented india's economy from taking
off by keeping it down the nerubian rate
of growth so what if he uh
imposed a colonial education system on
india those are very small things but we
should remember he was a great man
come on guys come on
look at the facts
the facts speak for themselves that's
all i have to say about shireen aruji
let's see some other questions
satoru says mr satoru gojo
what are the similarities between sound
waves and gravitational waves well waves
need a medium to travel in if you see
the surface of a pond or a lake or the
ocean you see the waves up and going up
and down and the medium is the body of
water that is the medium sound waves
propagate through the air if there is no
air if there is vacuum there is no sound
so sound waves are disturbances in
the medium that we are in the atmosphere
of the air
similarly the gravitational waves also
need a medium to propagate in and that
medium is space time it is the fabric of
space-time which is the fabric of the
universe
so so sound waves propagate
within
air
within the earth's atmosphere or the
atmosphere of any planet there is sound
on mars on venus etc so sound waves need
an atmosphere a gas
to propagate in and gravitational waves
need the medium of the space time
continuum to propagate in so that is the
difference between sound waves and
gravitational waves apart from that
similarities these are both waves these
are all disturbances in the medium in
which they propagate so that is the
similarity and the equations well there
are some similarities in the equations
if you look at them
if you look at the wave equation
uh
between
these two things so there are some
similarities the way the energy is
carried and momentum and all that you
know so there are similarities and there
are differences as well
all right let us see some more questions
i wish you all a very happy ganesha
turtle
pamorya everybody
uh i'm not sure if i can hear it but i
am in mumbai and there's this
celebration this festive atmosphere
everywhere i think the sound is coming
in through my walls i'm not in a studio
soundproof studio so maybe you'll hear
the sound of the celebrations well if
you do hear it i wish you all a very
happy ganesha turtle and
a great celebration a very happy
celebration of this great utsav
okay gaurav route says what happens if
scientists are able to
unify all the forces that exist in the
universe you know the forces are
actually all manifestations of the uh
one
original primordial force that was a
unified force that existed in the very
very
in the immediate aftermath of the big
bang
uh at time scales that are shorter than
10 raised to minus 44 seconds or minus
43 seconds so this
the force did exist at the time and then
the forces the the forces that we
observed that decoupled out of that
and scientists are still searching for
ways to unify the forces mathematically
to understand the origin of the universe
better
so if they are able to unify the forces
of the universe it will be done
mathematically on paper they will not
somehow make a machine that will unify
the forces that's almost impossible to
do because to do that you will have to
recreate the conditions of the big bang
energies during the big bang epoch were
so incredibly high that there is no way
in the known universe to recreate such
energies in a lab so it can only be done
mathematically it won't it is there's no
way
even a very advanced civilization or
species could actually recreate those
conditions in a lab i mean as far as we
know
so if it happens then we will understand
the universe better that's what is going
to happen maybe we'll be able to make
some technological progress etc using
that uh
newfound knowledge so that's what would
hap what will happen if scientists are
someday able
to
find discover
the grand unified force
dungar singh chauhan says that today was
the anniversary of the 9 11 bombings
what have we as a nation
learned
well
what have well the
primary learnings are for the united
states of america i think they were
taking
their security
rather lightly now after 9 11 they all
they tightened everything up
and so what did we learn we learned that
terrorism is a major uh tool in
certain nations
arsenal it can be used to
significantly uh
wound a nation and its public
consciousness
and we also learned that the americans
well we know what happened afterwards
you know the invasion of afghanistan and
the way this event was used by the
americans to expand their politic their
geopolitical footprint in the indian
subcontinent especially pakistan and
afghanistan at that time the united
states was not favorably disposed
towards india
it regarded india as an enemy as a
nation that needed it to be taught a
lesson so they made the best of this
they invaded afghanistan they set up
base there for 20 years
so that's what happened i mean
things are still in progress as we know
in afghanistan they're withdrawn etc so
what did we learn from this well
terrorism exists it can be used to
to bleed a country as we know better
than anybody else we have experienced 26
11 we have experienced numerous train
bombings numerous city bombings etc so
we we know these lessons much
better than the united states we have
experienced terrorism much more than the
u.s has ever experienced it
the us has had only one major
uh terrorist attack major terrorist
attack on u.s soil india has been bled
repeatedly since the 19 late 1980s
onwards it's only in the last seven or
eight years that this has stopped
because the current government the
current prime minister has made it very
clear if there is any terrorist strike
on india there's gonna be hell to pay
for pakistan and we know that terrorism
comes only from pakistan more or less
so i think this the current government
has
demonstrated that india can deal with
terrorism with a very uh
with a very hard hand and that is a very
good development that we have seen in
the past
seven eight years that's a very good
thing
okay
kapil says
a geopolitics question
regarding the emergency in sri lanka can
india offer to help them if they agree
to join india as a new state or
autonomous area should india pursue this
okay so what you're referring to is the
uh recently in the last week or so the
news has come out that sri lanka has
declared an economic
emergency
they are close to defaulting on the big
loans they have taken from especially
china i would say china has trapped them
in their customary debt debt trap
and yeah the sri lankans are maybe on
the verge of defaulting on certain loan
repayments i i'm not sure if it's
to try now or to the international
monetary fund or somebody else but they
are in a precarious situation right now
so the time is right for a country like
china to take over like even even
further by
you know offering
more loans in exchange for collateral
such as land and property and you know
that sort of thing
now can india offer to help if they
agree to join india as a new state the
sri lankans will want to weigh
the possibilities
who's running sri lanka right now it's
the rajapaksa family that is running
running sri lanka i think it is mr
gotabaya rajapaksa who is at the head
and his brother mr mahinda rajapaksa is
one of the major ministers but i think
mr mahinda rajapaksa is the real center
of power as far as i
can see
now when it is a strong man or a certain
family that is running a country it is
essentially
run for themselves it's they will take
um
they will take decisions based on their
personal interest rather on their
national interests they are known to be
rather corrupt i mean lots of reports
have come in the media it's not me
speaking it's not my opinion there's
been a lot written in the media about
the corruption that has been there in
sri lanka during the rajapaksas times
and even later and they are back again
inside in the saddle
so i think it is when you have a strong
man running a country or a family
running a country it's very easy to
offer them inducements
bribes
etc
which may not be
in the larger interest of the country
but it will be beneficial for the family
or the individual and that's what the
chinese have been doing and the
americans also have been doing in
pakistan and afghanistan in
africa and many other places that's how
geopolitics is played
now will the rajapaksas be willing to
give up sovereignty of their country to
india in exchange for help i don't think
so i think they'll be much more i'm
unable to getting further bribes from
the chinese in exchange for giving up
sovereignty to china
because
that's how the game is played the
chinese will ensure that the rajapaksa
stay in power etc for a long period of
time as long as they can keep ruling the
country
and enriching themselves it works for
them india probably will not offer such
a deal to them
so even if such an offer were on the
table i don't think it's going to work
out
right now at least
india needs to become way more powerful
it has to become the
only hegemonic power in the indian ocean
for such a scenario to be viable and for
a country like sri lanka to consider it
seriously
because loss of sovereignty explicitly
to india
would be something that even the sri
lankan public may not like
but
de facto loss loss of sovereignty to
china is what's already going on it's
not visible sri lanka doesn't officially
come under china and that's why it is
more palatable
so
in order to someday uh
create a larger confederation of nations
or a civilizational state india will
need to become much more powerful
economically militarily and have way
more influence geopolitically than it
currently has
that's what needs to happen
right let's see some more questions uh
first okay i can see some new members
thank you so much for joining i really
appreciate it and i would like to thank
all the current members also for having
become members thank you so much
and let me also thank all of you all of
you those of you who have been
contributing in various ways to the
channel i really appreciate it thank you
so much
all right let's see some more questions
says why is the world not sanctioning
pakistan despite knowing that they have
played a major role in the victory of
the taliban era and are also responsible
for terrorism in the subcontinent good
question why is the world not sanctioned
in pakistan this hashtag has been
trending on twitter for the past couple
of weeks sanctioned pakistan well the
world doesn't
the world is not run on the basis of
hashtags and social media trends and
sentiments the world is all about real
politic
and uh
geopolitics you know various
large hegemonic powers have certain
interests and those are the interests
they pursue now the world as we know has
been creating lots of terrorist outfits
not the world but the major powers of
the world if you look at the history of
the past 100 years they have created a
number of terrorist outfits used them
for some time then discarded them then
again reuse them when it was been useful
for them and so on al-qaeda had a use
the afghan mujahideen were a terrorist
outfit one could one could argue that
they were a terrorist outfit but they
were useful to the us so they were used
the taliban
has not
see the pakistanis have not
played a role in the victory of the
taliban the americans have handed over
the country of afghanistan to the
taliban they have ensured the taliban
get the best possible chance to rule the
country for the next 10 20 years
so it's not pakistan that has done that
it's the americans who have done that
now the question again is why is the
world not sanctioning pakistan
well
if you look at al-qaeda the americans
used al-qaeda they supported al-qaeda in
syria recently
right the u.s supported the taliban
in afghanistan
over at various points in time the
americans have turned a blind eye in the
1980s 90s and even the early 2000s
they have turned a blind eye to
pakistan's support of terrorism in
kashmir and other parts of india the
americans knew what was happening when
india complained they said it's a law
and order problem it's not terrorism
right so the americans and the world
larger large world powers major powers
have always known that terrorism exists
and terrorism is a tool they use from
time to time to pursue and further their
national interest globally
and out of all these terrorist outfits
that the western world has created
in the past many decades
the biggest terrorist outfit is the
pakistan army
and that was the stick they used to beat
india with
time and time again
right
so if they have created this stick to
beat india with they will not want to
see the stick being destroyed as long as
it is useful in some way or the other
even today
they will want to keep pressurizing
india in certain ways
and they will use pakistan for that
pakistan is still is potentially useful
to these people
and therefore pakistan is a tool that
they will want to sustain
at least for the time being the
americans may not have much use for the
pakistanis anymore i would say but now
the chinese have a use for the
pakistanis because the chinese want to
keep india off balance and they want to
have this pain point pressure pressure
point on india at the western border
and the chinese are therefore supporting
the pakistanis
and these are the reasons why the major
parts of the world
keep using these bad guys the terrorists
the dictators and so on
in the world the world needs bad people
these major powers need bad guys from in
various places
in order to run the world because there
are certain things you can do officially
in a democratic liberal society but you
can give covert support to certain
terrorists to do certain by certain
dirty jobs for you and so on so these
are the this is the way in which
geopolitics is played
much of it is below the table
and that is why the world is not
sanctioning pakistan
even though it is well known that they
are a terrorist nation
that is the answer my friends
okay what else do we have
mahesh patil says
tell us about the haksha manish dynasty
its contributions
and good books to read about them uh
okay first of all i don't see the okay
first of all what is the haksha manish
dynasty the haksha manish dynasty is the
k minute dynasty it's called the
akaminate dynasty in the west
it is the dynasty the foundational
dynasty of persia so to say it is the
first major dynasty that
emerged in persia about three thousand
or so years ago
uh their
first king the founder king of this
dynasty was hakka manish
and that's why it's called the champions
dynasty or the akke minute dynasty they
the greeks called him a cheminus because
they like to distort
names right so the cabinet dynasty of
persia so it was a major dynasty they
had great kings like cyrus the great
which is who is kurosh the great
the raya who's the great darya is the
great
uh was there then you had
artaksatra or artha zerksist zexus you
had shayarsha or xerxes in greek and so
on so they had many great kings they
built a great empire they even went to
war with the romans and the greeks
mostly the greeks but at some point in
time they even fought the romans so they
had a large sphere of influence west of
india towards uh so called greater iran
which is uh if you see that let's say
let's take a look at the map the map is
always useful
so here is iran or persia
so there their empire was on the borders
of india at some points in time it
incorporated parts of afghanistan parts
of present-day pakistan and much of
present-day iran and even parts of
armenia georgia at one point in time it
had taken over the entirety of anatolia
uh in the uh middle of the fourth or
fifth century bce
and so on so it was a very significant
dynasty they had many great achievements
they adopted zoroastrianisms of me which
means that they gave up
uh they transitioned from hinduism to
zoroastrianism
was born i think in balik
in bulk if i am not mistaken it was in
afghanistan that he was born or maybe in
herat
either bulk or herat
so he was born in india in gandhar
because 3000 years ago afghanistan was
very much part of india it was gandhar
so zarathustra was an indian he was born
there then he managed to influence the
people of persia the parshwa people and
they adopted his uh
his his
belief system which is now known as
zoroastrianism
so that is what happened so he was born
in hindu the persons were hindus and
then the transition to zoroastrianism so
that is something about the haksha
manish or akhemin dynasty it is during
their time that this religion
zoroastrianism came to the fore and it
was it spread throughout the persian
world
uh any good books to read about them i
i mean i have read so many books i can't
think of one good book or one single
book in which you can get to get to read
all about them i would say books by will
durant especially about asia could be
useful
i i i seriously don't have a single book
one book or two books or three books
that i can give off the top of my head
that you can
use to learn about this i mean
i have read so many books so i can't
think of any one book maybe you can
start with if it is available uh one of
the books so will durant has this series
of books called the story of
civilization i think
and
so that has a great deal of information
about
ancient porsche as well one of the books
in that i think it is
our asian heritage or something like
that you can check it out so that is one
of the books i could recommend it's an
it's an old book maybe almost 100 years
old but it is still very useful it's got
a lot of great information
so maybe that you could start with that
but i i'm sorry i cannot
i can't recall any one book i've read so
many so
i'm not very good at book
recommendations if i recommend books i
love to recommend 20 or 30 books
which i can't recall right now so
apologies for that
okay
dhruv mishra says please elaborate on
the navy's importance and what india can
do to power it up and become
a leader let's look at the map
if we see india today
this here is india this is the indian
ocean region if you see india
you will see that it is almost cut off
from asia
on the west and in the north you have
the border with pakistan so we can't use
that border to go anywhere because it's
a highly
militarized border
and to the north you have pakistan
occupied kashmir which is again highly
militarized
to the north and the east you have the
border of tibet which is occupied by
china so that again is a very
militarized border very tense border you
know what's been happening there
so there is no way to access asia or
other parts of the world through there
if you look at the northeast of india
there is very little infrastructure
there are very few roads
the burma the burma border is very
thickly forested there is only one road
i think into burma through india and
that is through the town of moray in
manipur again the roads are very bad we
would
there's been talk of building a four
lane or express highway that will
connect uh more
to southeast asia and even a railway
line i don't know what's happening it's
been
they have been talking about it for the
past 20 years i don't know how much it
has progressed
so india essentially now we have
bangladesh again which is eastern
bengal which is again we don't have much
land access there right
so if you look at india it is almost cut
off
from the rest of the world through land
we have no railways that take us to
europe or to to the east
we have no roads that help us access the
rest of the world
the only way indians travel outside of
india is by air
so and yet we have this enormous
coastline we have this beautifully god
this beautiful god-given position
in the center of eurasia
which straddles the entire indian ocean
so why doesn't india become a maritime
superpower it we have everything we need
to become a maritime superpower that
would
expand our sphere of influence so
greatly
it would allow us to counter balance
china if china comes does the you know
play some mischief on the northern
border we can cut off china's access to
the rest of the world through the indian
ocean through the malacca strait for
instance right so the malacca straight
through this stay straight over here
over here
i think it's called the strait of sunda
i think if i'm not mistaken or something
else and of course we have the strait of
hormuz here and
and this here baba al-mandeb so we have
access to all of these choke points that
can make china behave but you need a
powerful navy for that if you look at
the present-day strength of the navy
it's not much i know i have got lots of
comments but people say no we have a big
navy i mean come on
the strength of the navy is not how many
ships you have even though we don't have
so many ships
the strength of the navy is how many
missiles you can field at sea on a given
day
right
and if you look at the
actual number of missiles we can feel on
any given day it is not much if you look
at the number of dangerous deadly ships
like destroyers we have it's just a
handful
if you look at the number of submarines
we have 15 or 16 working submarines the
chinese have many more times than that
submarines even the japanese have more
submarines than india even the north
koreans have 80 or 90 submarines at work
so india
has
done a very bad job
of developing its marine strength its
maritime naval strength
what india needs to do
is invest in
agile platforms that can deploy missiles
missile boats lighter ships etc right
now the navy is more or less just a
glorified coast guard that's all it is
we have one aircraft carrier that we
have to hide in during war time
because it is an enormous thing and it's
a very big target it's an enticing
target i think in the in the 71 war we
had to hide the aircraft carrier in the
eastern sea in the bay of bengal near
vishakapatnam
so aircraft carriers are just nice white
elephants they don't really serve much
use in war it's a very big target if the
enemy is able to destroy your aircraft
carrier half your naval strength is
going right there
the entire
basis
of a strong navy is distributed
lethality but india is investing in
concentrating its ledality in one or two
large ships like aircraft carriers at in
my opinion
india doesn't even need an aircraft
carrier india needs to invest in smaller
lighter agile ships that can carry lots
of missiles and it is it needs to
populate the entire indian ocean region
with lots and lots of ships quantity has
a quality of its own
right
if you have
one let's say you have 10 destroyers
that can each carry 16 brahmos missiles
so you have 160 brahmos missiles that
you can deploy and not every destroyer
can be deployed at sea on a given day
usually it's one third or one half that
you can just play deploy
but instead of that if you had let's say
a hundred missile boats that can each
carry three brahmos missiles then
imagine how much you can spread out your
lethality across the indian ocean so
these are some of the things that india
needs to look into india has done very
badly in in creating a strong navy our
naval
officers are brilliant they are very
well trained they are very professional
they are second to none but
unfortunately they don't have to have
the kind of resources at their disposal
we would like to see lots of new ships
dangerous deadly powerful ships and that
would
make india a significant geopolitical
player in in about a decade if india
were to invest in that and india needs
to
build a lot more submarines
so that's why the navy is important it
gives you the kind of power across a
very large
percentage of the globe
if you
invest
in building a strong navy that's why
it's important
all right let's see some more questions
can we nuke pakistan we can nuke
pakistan but it is not desirable you
shouldn't nuclear weapons are
they are not
they are not created to be used in
warfare it is a deterrent
it is something that tells the enemy
that you cannot cross a certain line a
certain red line if you do cross that
red line you're done
so it's a deterrent it's not supposed to
be used ever we don't want to nuke
pakistan we don't want the pakistanis to
die they are our brothers and sisters no
matter what they believe they are still
our
people i do not wish the people of
pakistan ill i want them to be happy i
want them to prosper but i want pakistan
to be fragmented and broken up because
that is going to eliminate the role of
the pakistan army which is oppressing
the people of pakistan and creating this
sense of conflict between india and them
i would like to see
a an independent synth an independent
balochistan an independent punjab i
would like to see poke come back to
india they'll get both the sun come back
to india and i would like to see the
pashtun areas go back to afghanistan
that is what needs to happen the world
will be at peace if we can make this
happen it we don't need to nuke pakistan
in order for this to happen
we want pakista the people of pakistan
to have a good life but
in independent nations like sindh and
balochistan and punjab so nuking them is
not the solution
it's like
if the only
tool you have as a hammer then every
problem you see is a nail that's not how
it works we have a big
diverse tool kit of tools and we need to
use all the tools in our arsenal and if
some tools are not strong enough we need
to strengthen them
and that's what needs to happen so yeah
we can nuke pakistan if we want to we
can nuke china also if we want to but is
it desirable we're going to have some
blow back too that's not the way to do
things you know we need to have a more
nuanced approach towards geopolitics
raghav says what is the outcome of being
swallowed by a black hole
well
if you are swallowed by a black hole
what's interesting is what happens
before you are slow followed by a black
hole
if the black hole is large enough if
it's a super massive black hole
then you won't even realize when you
cross the event horizon the event
horizon is just a it's not a real
thing it's it's just
the point of no return beyond which even
light cannot come back
beyond which even light cannot turn back
and escape the black hole so it's a
theoretical boundary it's a physical
region but there is no actual surface
you know it's just
it's just a distance from the center now
before you are swallowed by a black hole
if it is a reasonably small black hole
not a supermassive one then you will
undergo something called
spaghettification
it is because of tidal forces when you
let's say you have a pencil or a pen
now
this pen is
it is being affected by the earth's
gravity
if i
leave it it will drop down it will drop
towards the center of the earth
now the force of gravity at the at the
bottom of the pen is slightly greater
than the force that the top of the pen
is feeling because the top of the pen is
slightly more distant from the center of
the earth than the bottom of the pen
but the difference in the gravitational
field strength is very very very minimal
it can't really be measured but in the
case of a black hole
this distance from here to here is very
significant the force that is felt over
here
if i if this pen is near a black hole is
very much stronger than the force the
head will feel and therefore this pen
will get stretched out a little
elongated now if a human being were to
fall into it
the four and let's see let's say the
person is falling in
feet first
then the force your feet feel the
gravitational force your feet will feel
will be maybe 10 or 100 times greater
than the force your head will feel and
therefore your body will be stretched
out in spaghetti fight it's called
spaghettification
and therefore
much before you reach
the
event horizon of a black hole you're
going to be stretched out into long
strands of spaghetti which is not a good
thing to imagine
because it's gonna be the end of you so
that is the outcome
of somebody who's in the process of
falling into a black hole they'll get
stretched out and spaghettified into
long long strands of
well human substance
but if you are able to go inside
a black hole if it's a supermassive one
intact
then at some point in time you will
encounter something really strange in
that we don't really know what it is
according to the best physics that we
have the equations of
the general theory of relativity there
is something called a singularity at the
heart of a black hole
but that is
most likely just a mathematical artifact
that tells us that there is something
missing in our theory
so there is something inside a black
hole we don't quite know what it is
that's why it's black because
we can only speculate what's beyond the
event horizon so that's what i can say
you may find some strange
what may be on the other side maybe
there's a white hole on the other side
of a black hole maybe it's a portal to
another universe maybe there's a whole
wormhole inside that will take you to
another part of the universe
maybe
but that's all
that is all
speculation because we don't quite know
so what we can say for sure is that you
will get spaghettified while going
inside but once you cross the event
horizon if you stay conscious if you're
still alive we don't know what happens
because
our
best theories still cannot explain
what's inside
all right what else do we have
some more questions
interesting
please tell us about ancient indian diet
and the cuisine well
unfortunately we don't have ancient
cookbooks that go back two thousand
three thousand years unfortunately but
uh some people have done some analysis
of some pottery et cetera found
in the
uh saraswati sindhu region the sindhu
region of ancient india so they found
harappan era pottery and they did some
chemical analysis and they were able to
reconstruct one of the ancient dishes
that somebody had made it was i think
eggplant brinjal
with
with ginger and turmeric
in in some some sort of oil so that's
the kind of residue they were able to
find
in that
in that vessel
and i remember seeing some other
news report
or some article i think in nature i
think in which they found seven ancient
fossilized
ladoos
you know
multi-grain ladoos in in the same
geography of india which is in the
region so it's clear that indians were
eating laddus multi-grain leaders maybe
five six thousand years before today so
there is clearly again this is another
data point that points to the continuity
of culture in the indian subcontinent
going back several thousand years to the
very beginnings of the so-called
harappan era
so that's what we know that indians did
eat a very similar
diet similar to what they we eat even
today even today ladoos are very popular
right
right now we have this ganesh festival
going what is lord ganesha's favorite
food it's the laddu
so
so yeah it's interesting that this
cultural continuity is seen that goes
back many thousand years
but it's interesting i wish some
historians and some researchers would
actually do more detailed research into
deciphering the exact kind of diet that
we had
in ancient times i am sure that if you
look at if you take some
ancient remains from the harappan
saptasana region many remains are
available and you do spectroscopic
analysis of the bones the teeth then you
can i'm sure you can determine what sort
of
minerals and other other
uh such elements were present in the
diet
so i wish that would be done but so far
our historians have done nothing i think
it's up to the scientists to decipher
what our history really was like
okay
let us
see some more
questions
sc says
why does atheism exist
why were different religions formed are
there many gods in the universe where is
god in the universe or the multiverse
okay let me answer the first question
first why does atheism exist because
people are skeptical by nature
god isn't something physical right have
you ever seen god
i have never seen god i have never seen
a physical manifestation of god or gods
it is all about belief right religion is
about belief whether you believe
in a god or not or multiple gods or
whatever manifestation
of the divine essence or whatever you
want to call it that is something that
comes from within you or it comes from
within your culture
but there's always people in any culture
who are skeptical
and
even in various indian philosophies
one of the most basic and most
simplest indian philosophies is charvaka
which is pure materialism
whatever you see is what exists there is
nothing else
that is atheism
it is a highly skeptical theory
a skeptical philosophy but there's a
logic to it so philosophy is about logic
it's about a logical school of thought
and there are other um
atheistic or agnostic schools of thought
like both the dharma both the philosophy
jaina philosophy and many more there are
various more i have got you can
see my five-minute intro to philosophy
indian philosophy on this channel look
it up i've given some a brief amount of
detail about that so atheism exists i
mean any in any culture in any religious
uh
structure you're gonna have people who
don't believe
so that's why atheism exists
and in in uh what is now called hinduism
atheism is very much a part of hinduism
if there are multiple atheistic schools
of thought so that is very much part of
it
i think even mansa
believes that the universe
is run by the law of karma but there is
no divine essence there is no creator
god
so that's what it is you know and the
hinduism or the
dharmic
uh
the dharmic schools of thought
or the dharmic culture or civilization
is what
uh
it
respects
all kinds of viewpoints and perspectives
and you will find that nowhere else in
the world
especially not in any abrahamic school
of thought in any abrahamic religion so
why were different religions formed well
because
see in in india we don't have religions
we have philosophical schools of thought
both the
school of thought the jaina school of
thought
vedanta etc you know charvaka so these
are different schools of thought these
are not different religions now the
westerners have tried to break it up
into hinduism buddhism
jainism now they're trying to create
more divide divisions like brahmanism
and dalitism and god knows what else
so they are trying to divide indian
culture in the indian society in this
manner to break it apart
but outside of india especially in west
asia etc well these different prophets
emerged the the earliest prophet that we
know of was zarathustra
or zoroaster who said that he received a
vision from from ahura mazda the god
that he believed in and this became the
first revealed religion and then you had
these various various
semitic or abrahamic religions
three of them which you know of
so these are all
these all emerge in the in the
socio-political context of that
geographical region which was the desert
areas of the middle east so that's why
these religions are highly militarized
highly structured
and there is no ques no no space for
questioning and and all that
so the entire attitude is very different
there
so these are the socio-political and
socio-cultural
forces that create
these belief systems or religions
it all depends on the on the kind of
climate and geography and and much more
that you have
where this
emerges
now are there many gods in the universe
where is god listen i don't know
our scriptures
the dharmic scriptures say a lot of
things about god or gods in the rig veda
itself there is the nasa
that says that
there is essentially
agnosticism
it says that we don't quite know who
made the universe
it likens in the rigveda the
the creation of the universe is likened
to the uh
to the way a blacksmith forges
an instrument
in his fire
but it's it it's quite agnostic that we
don't know what came before the universe
and if somebody made the universe who
made him that's the kind of question
that is asked in the rig rigveda so that
is quite agnostic but later on you have
very clear
a very clear polytheistic
pantheon which is the original
polytheistic pantheon of the entire
indo-european world
in which indira was the most powerful
god who later became
so indra took
certain aspects of dios pita
and dios pita became zeus peter in
greece zeus peter became jupiter in rome
and that eventually became thor in the
nordic world so we have this ancient
pantheon which is the original pantheon
that gave rise to the greek the roman
and the norse pantheon and even the
slavic pantheon
but are these real gods of do i mean
maybe
i don't know personally i have never
seen any of them but my senses are very
limited
i only have five senses we don't know
what's out there in the universe
95 of the universe is dark to us we
don't know what's out there
and our senses are very
very very uh primitive
they're very limited
so we don't know what's out there maybe
there are gods maybe there are lots of
gods maybe there's just one god
maybe there's no god who knows i don't
know i am nobody to say i am just a
student i am learning i am trying to
figure out what the world is like so i
don't have the answers to that how many
gods are there and whether there is a
god in the universe or multiverse we
don't know i don't know maybe some
people have it figured out i don't
so that's all all i can say about that
okay
ravi says talk about the japanese
brutality in china
yeah that's a very very uh curious thing
isn't it
so i had spoken about in the past of the
fact that asian empires
asian kings and asian emperors and asian
empires never indulged in colonialism i
gave the examples of the cholas the
cholas conquered the whole of southeast
asia but they did not ever extract any
wealth out of there they did not commit
any genocide or any massacres they
actually enrich the cultures they
actually the culture and the people of
the region they actually settled down
there the people of indonesia all have
indian
genetics the people of southeast asia
whether it's cambodia whether it is
thailand whether it is uh
vietnam etc laos myanmar they all have
indian indian blood
some percentage of indian dna and they
all are immersed in indian culture so
india gave more than it ever took it
took nothing and even the chinese did
not indulge in colonialism they did
conquer various parts of asia from time
to time but they did not extract wealth
out of there and neither did the great
mongols the great changes khan
otherwise mongolia would be a very rich
country today
and yet
there is a period in asian history
in which japan indulged in colonialism
which is in the early part of the 20th
century so the context to that is the
meiji reformation in which the meiji
emperor of japan in the late 18th
century tried to reconfigure japan
as uh in the western way so he tried to
imitate the west he tried to create an
industrialized society he tried to stamp
out buddhism which shows very much that
he was going against dharma
he tried to stamp out buddhism he failed
but then the entire approach of the
japan japan's imperial
machinery including the imperial army
was very much anti-dharmic or adharmic
and that's why that is what impelled
them into the these actions that they
that they are known to have
taken
in china and other places so yes they
were very brutal they were very brutal
you know what they did in nanjing
i mean the kind of behavior they
demonstrated in the city of nanjing
in china is is
abominable it is unforgivable we know
what they did in the in korea
what they did to the women of korea
it is barbaric brutal behavior
it is a great dark spot on the otherwise
good history of japan so it happened
because they turned away from their
dharmic culture the culture they had
been following for for 1500 years
and they went down they descended into
the depths of animalistic behavior
so that's what happened in japan the
brutality is like
unspeakable what they did in china i
mean and and the brutality that they did
even against various prisoners of war
during the second world war against
americans against australians against
indians as well
this is horrible what they did you know
and even the what they did in the in the
andam undercover islands
the way they treated the prisoners there
and all that it's absolutely brutal
so
whatever
so i i'm not sure if it's it's a karmic
thing that they were nuked in world war
ii
but it is a good thing that they were
defeated
in the second world war
they were on the doorstep of india
they wanted to conquer india and turn
turn india into a colony they wanted to
snatch india from the british and turn
india into their colony if they had
succeeded god knows what they would have
they would have done in india as well
so i think it's a good thing they lost
unfortunately the indian national army
so washington ina also lost as in the
process
but that's just how it went
so yes the the this is a very very
depressing and and
distressing chapter of history the
japanese behavior in the first half of
the 20th century terrible abominable
unforgivable
okay some more questions
some more questions
weibov says who was or is your favorite
us president or any other world leader
from the past 100 years
and why
well i don't have any
favorite
us president i think the most
significant one was abraham lincoln
uh
i don't have any favorites as such but i
would say the one of the most
significant ones is abraham lincoln
because the country was on was being on
the verge of being partitioned between
the north and the south and he went to
war to stop the partition of the country
and he was able to keep it together so
that's a very significant event and then
you had people like roosevelt eisenhower
kennedy to some extent nixon
many people who did
a great deal of who contributed a great
deal of
work to the country and who shaped the
court of the world because the u.s
became
a major superpower
uh apart from that who is my other
world leaders well there are many
significant world leaders
whether you like him or not winston
churchill was one of the significant
people he was a monster he
well he caused genocide in india more
than five i would say nearly 10 million
bengal has died directly as a
consequence of his actions so he was a
great monster hitler was a great monster
stalin was a great monster
so was mr maaw setong
lee kuan yew is a very interesting and
important figure
he brought this small city state of
singapore out of abject poverty and
destitution and he transformed it within
20 years into a first world nation so
there's a great deal to learn from him
another great leader is mustafa kemal
who took
this fragmented country
this ruined country turkey which was
which had been divided up
in the aftermath of the first world war
after the collapse of the ottoman empire
so he took this broken country and he
forged the unified nation out of it
mustafa kamal ataturk great man he tried
his best to secularize turkey but today
as you can see it has gone back full
circle and turkey has become again
it's reverting to its ottoman
ottoman mindset and culture
but he was a great man for sure mustafa
kemal
so there are many great leaders i i'm
sure i've missed many i'm not able to
think of all of them at the same time
but
there are many great leaders that even
that were there in the 20th century in
the past hundred years
i would say
was one of the greats
definitely one of the greats
and jinnah muhammad ali jinnah
tried to emulate ataturk that he was a
very very
poor version of
the colossus jinnah was a nobody it is
the british
who
contributed the greatest
to the success of jinnah
so it is not really jinnah who
caused the partition of india
it is the british and mr gandhi more
than mr jinnah
who partitioned india
okay
let's see some more questions
um let's see let's see let's see
jeevan rosario says did the people of
the middle ages have any perception of
live audio or visual recordings like
radio tv no
as far as we know there was no such
thing
we have found no evidence
of any such technology
harsh says what was the reason for giant
versions of current animal species in
the earlier eras of the earth on the
earth like elephants rhinos etc so yeah
in the past you had these mammoths wooly
mammoths that populated the colder
regions of eurasia and i think even
north america if i'm
if i'm not quite mistaken
then you had what's known as megafauna
giant uh versions of various animals
giant uh sloths
called megatherium and all who were
wiped out into
extinct who were forced into extinction
by our ancient ancestors from
many 10 000 years ago and so on so and
then you had these great sharks called
called the meg megalodon i think and you
had giant crocodiles and all so and you
also had the titanoboa these enormous
pythons that were like 10 times greater
than
10 times larger than any python alive
today
and you had enormous apes also i think
in the himalayas etc
so yes there were phases
in our planet's history where you had
this megaphone enormous animal species
even today you have some megaphone like
the blue whale which is the largest
animal known to have ever existed
on the planet so this is all because of
evolution there are certain times when
certain animals grow really large
because it is beneficial for them to
grow large for example when the wa maybe
the climatic conditions are such that it
is
beneficial for animals to grow large
in that case they grow larger and larger
but when some
of intelligent
predator emerges like like homo sapiens
or homo habilis or whatever then these
large animals become easy pickings for
them especially if they learn how to
hunt in groups and that's why these
large animals died out because of our
actions or the actions of our ancestors
and so on so these are evolutionary
cycles evolution
is often cyclic just like history is
cyclic but the cycles of evolution
happen over millions of years
maybe tens of millions of years just the
way that the cycles of history happen
over decades or centuries so it's in a
way similar to the cycles of history so
it's all about the forces of evolution
the evolutionary forces that
you have this thing called the
milkanovich cycle in which the climate
of the earth goes from hot to cold or
many thousands of years and so on so
so climate is cyclic you have periods of
of hot climate then you have periods of
ice ages
and that's what causes the
changes
in the body structures and sizes of
animals
and that's what we witness in the fossil
record so it is all
because of the forces of evolution
survival of the fittest the climate is
changing animals have to adapt
and to adapt they have to either change
their size of the behavior or come up
with new mutations
or new
uh evolutionary
changes so that's what causes that
okay let's
see some more question
you are most welcome marsh
jorge says
could you talk about the import
importance of kautilya and the
arthashastra for india political theory
and international relations you know it
is very important these lessons that we
find in the arthashastra especially
when it comes to
geopolitics kut niti
and all that these are timeless lessons
these are applicable even today
there are seminars in
in military schools and colleges and
universities in the west
about the principles
of the arthashaster the principles of
vishnu gupta but in india
i don't think there is any military
university or college in india in which
these precepts are taught
and even when it comes to politicians
and and people in diplomacy etc i don't
think it's required reading for them
i know the arthashastra is
a large book it deals with all kinds of
topics which are all related to
statecraft with the
with how to run a kingdom
but when it comes to
geopolitics and international relations
there are certain sections that are
would be quite quite useful for people
who are
on the front lines in these fields
so it's very important and
i i would say that you know in the past
70 years
countries like pakistan and china have
been
they have been doing better at china
than india they have been
adhering to the principles and the
precepts of chanakaniti far better than
india which is a crying shame
so i think it is very very important
that
we take
the teachings of the great vishnu gupta
chanakya very seriously these are
timeless teachings if the world still
exists if human if humanity still exists
2000 years in the future these precepts
will
will be just as useful 2000 years from
today
so these are timeless concepts and these
have to be taken very seriously if india
starts implementing
chanakya niti in its true sense
across the sphere in geopolitics and
international relations india will be a
very different kind of country
so it is very important that's this is a
very good question
this is another interesting question by
naman
can you comment on the establishment of
portuguese power in india and why any
other european power was not able to
discover india in the 15th century
so in the 1490s you had this age of
discovery the europeans were going
hither and thither
looking for
ways to rediscover india
constantinople had fallen to the turks
the byzantine empire was dead and the
land route to india had been cut off
and the europeans had been trading with
india for thousands of years
a significant portion of the roman
empire's trade was with india they would
import spices and other goods and
various other things from india and they
would give back gold in return and
that's how india became enormously
wealthy by trading with all these
different countries
so the europeans loved indian products
spices and other things
and when the turks cut off the land
route to india it was a crisis point for
them
and so
this triggered off the age of discovery
so christopher columbus
was looking for india
his objective
was to discover and colonize india
but he blundered off in the wrong
direction he found the americas and he
came back and reported that he had
discovered india to
isabella and ferdinand of spain the king
and queen of the queen and king of spain
and similarly the portuguese were also
looking for india now christopher
columbus went westwards across the
atlantic ocean he thought that maybe he
will discover india from there
and what was the gamma the portuguese
thought that he would go go around
africa and try to find
a way to reach india through that
and
he happened to succeed he was able to go
around the cape of good hope
he reached i think zanzibar or somewhere
where there was a significant indian
presence for centuries or even millennia
because
we we know that there has been indian
presence and influence in africa for at
least 4 000 years so he found indians
there i think the person he found was
either gujarati or from kerala
and he took this merchant with him on
his ship
and this this merchant was able to
show
the government the way to reach india
and that's how he reached calicut
so that's how he was able to discover
india
so he went in the right direction he got
lucky and that's how he was able to
discover india so the portuguese then
started trading with india they started
creating these colonies in india their
objective was to colonize and destroy
india and plunder all its wealth which
has been the which was the objective of
every single european power so columbus
also wanted to colonize india
and later on the british because of
their technological prowess
were able to overpower all the other
european powers and
take india for their own so that's what
happened
in
the about 500 years from before today
that's what happened
joydip says how did the dinosaurs
disappear
well joy
who tells you that the dinosaurs
disappeared
i see them every day
they are everywhere
dinosaurs are still alive they are
everywhere
the non-avian dinosaurs died out but the
avian dinosaurs survived
they had feathers they are called birds
today birds are the descendants of the
dinosaurs who survived the cataclysm
that occurred 66 million years ago
so what happened to the other dinosaurs
so there was this enormous
cometary impact we believe it's it was a
comet
the
comet which impacted the earth about 66
billion years ago the impact was in the
yucatan peninsula let me show you the
region
let me show you the map so if we go west
to let's go west we could even have gold
eastwards but it's fine
so this is
mexico here as you can see this is
mexico and here you have this peninsula
it's called the yucatan peninsula this
state is called yucatan and this
peninsula is called the yucatan
peninsula
and if you go here
if you go further
it's somewhere here that you will find
the village of chichulub
let me see where it is where it is where
is it where is it let me search for it
c-h-i-c
yucatan
here it is
so this little village
in mexico is called chikshulob it is at
the epicenter
of an ancient impact event that happened
66 million years ago
it was here
and the crater is now buried under the
ocean under the ocean and also under
land
but it is faint it may be faintly
visible here it's an enormous crater
about 130 or 180 kilometers in diameter
so this is where the impact happened
66 billion years ago and it is believed
that this impact contributed
to the extinction of almost
to the majority of species that were
alive on our planet at that time and
that includes all the non-avian
dinosaurs
so some species survived this this
impact event
it was like a nuclear winter
you know
the entire world was shrouded in
a thick blanket of smoke and suit and
dust and whatnot and this may have gone
on for about a decade or so so there was
a period of about a decade possibly
in which there was no sunlight on the
planet the planet froze almost
and only some species of animals
survived
including the avian dinosaurs who are
the ancestors of today's birds
and also some small rat like
mammals survived these little rat like
mammals survived by scavenging on the
dead bodies of dinosaurs and other
things
and those rat like mammals
made it through this period and their
descendants are talking to you today we
are their descendants
so our ancestors survived
that horrific impact event
but the majority of species on the
planet died out
because it was a devastating
devastating impact
the comet or asteroid that struck the
earth was at least 10 kilometers in
diameter that's enormous
and it struck the planet about 50 or 60
kilometers per second
and the
the
explosion that resulted out of this was
like
millions of times greater than the most
powerful nuclear bomb ever exploded it
caused an enormous
hyper tsunami
that tsunami was two or three kilometers
tall
and the speed of the tsunami was
greater than the speed of sound
so it was a
supersonic hyper tsunami and the shock
wave went across the planet many many
times
the entire planet's crust rung like a
bell
and you had volcanic explosions
everywhere because of this and at that
time there was also
uh
a super volcano in progress
somewhere in this region in the middle
of the indian ocean
at that time india
was drifting away from us from africa
and it was it had not yet
it had not yet collided with asia so
india at that time the indian peninsula
was an island in the middle of the
indian ocean
and at that time you had this super
volcano in india called the deccan traps
so if you go into central india today
into the deccan plateau whether it is in
maharashtra or or telangana karnataka
you see this ancient volcanic
outcrops and rocks and the western ghats
and all that these are the remnants of
the dick and traps super volcano
explosion or eruption that also happened
about 66 million years ago so that also
may have contributed in some way to the
extinction of the dinosaurs
so it was maybe simply the impact that
did it or maybe it was also the
the uh
contribution of that super volcano
explosion in india that may also have
contributed to the extinction
of most of the species
that were alive at that time so that is
in brief about this question
anuj pandey says your favorite indian
personalities in the past 200 years that
is a very tough question
the one thing india has lacked in the
past 1000 years is towering leaders
in the past 200 years i've been
favorite indian personalities
i it's it's very hard for me to think of
anybody i admire in the past 200 years
the last great indian i admired was
chatrapati shivaji maharaj
who else
is worthy of admiration maybe subhashin
rabos the great nitaji maybe he was
he was certainly somebody who put his
life his reputation everything on the
line
for the sake of the country so yes
he is somebody worth admiring for sure
sebastian rabos
i apologize if i'm missing out any
significant personalities
uh
not sharing erogee certainly not mr nero
who else in the past 200 years
i really can't think
of nobody comes to mind straight away
apart from sebastian rabos
unfortunately
so yeah i'll just stay keep it at that
and maybe in the future i'll think of it
i'll rack my
my mind and my memory
to try and think of some great people
what is your opinion i would like to see
your opinion in the comments who do you
think who whom do you admire
in india in the past 200 years okay
swami vivekananda
was a very prominent scientist yes one
it is good that you brought up mr abdul
galam's name here
a great scientist a great engineer mr
swami vivekananda the great uh scholar a
great
spiritual leader great like to see that
mr sauvarkar
great good to see mr ramanujan srinivasa
ramanujan
you're saying
i can see some funny things as well
netaji lal badou shastra good bhagat
singh
bhagat singh died very young bhagat
singh died so young right he was 23 when
he died today people say i was on a
debate a couple of days ago
i was on a i was on a debate a
discussion about
whether india's partition was
whether it was was it inevitable
or could have been could it have been
prevented this was a discussion between
me and
a gentleman from from a pakistani
gentleman from sweden
a pakistani gentleman from the us
a jnu professor from india and an indian
politician
and me so we had this debate about who
whether partition was was inevitable or
not
and i said that the moment subhash
chandra bose was sidelined by the
congress party at that time partition
became even inevitable because many
people who fought against
subhashin-rabos
eventually
became pakistanis but had he won
then they would have remained indians
so i said that subhashin
once he was sidelined india's partition
became more or less inevitable and one
of the pakistani gentlemen was saying
that
was nobody
bhagat singh said that sebastian rabos
was nobody because he nehru was more
prominent according to bhagat singh
that's what the pakistani gentleman said
and my point to him was that bhagat
singh was a bacha when he died he was 23
at the age of 23 you don't have the
world figured out you're still exploring
things
bhagat singh died at the age of 23 if he
was alive today he would not even speak
to him
so that's the point you know bhagat
singh was a great great patriot
he he gave the ultimate sacrifice for
the sake of his
of his motherland
and he was so young so yeah he he was a
great patriot certainly somebody worth
remembering and somebody worth admiring
sarvopali radhakrishnan good
chandrashekar azad another great martyr
another man who gave his life for the
country
sri aurobindo gosh interesting choice
definitely a great scholar
i haven't studied him
in the amount of detail i would want to
study somebody before i come to a
conclusion but yes definitely somebody
who is greatly admired by people in
india shri aurobindo ghosh definitely
lots of people admire him
good good nice to nice to see that very
good very good
great great a great sick warrior great
warrior
nice to see swabashi peshwa good good
who else
and so on
good good to see all your
questions all of your uh
opinions
although says where did you debate it
was on a channel called the
argumentative indians it's a small
channel
uh so that's where the debate was held
it was like a couple of days ago
it was i think in the beginning of this
week
maybe monday or tuesday i don't remember
it's a channel called the argumentative
indians
okay so yeah so many
interesting opinions
thank you for your opinions very
interesting to see that very nice
okay let me stick let me take some more
questions from you
uh
let me see some more questions
swaraj says how can we get back p-o-k
well in one sentence by following chanak
kennedy and being patient
that's how we get back p okay it won't
happen
in the next six months it won't happen
in the next two years
it can happen in the next
five to ten years
if we
are patient
and if we follow the principles
of
vishnu gupta chanakya
properly
in a calm
measured step-by-step fashion it can
certainly happen in the next five to ten
years
pawan says bhavan asks why didn't
indians try conquering africa like the
chulas did southeast asia
well i don't really have
an absolute answer for that indians did
trade with africa
i think we have been trading with africa
for two three four thousand years
there is
of significant and very deep cultural
substratum in africa in eastern africa
that is indian and origin look at the
cuisine in eastern africa let's take a
look at eastern africa
so if we go here you have somalia
tanzania mozambique madagascar
uh this kenya kenya and so on ethiopia
if you look at the culture of eastern
africa whether it's in somalia kenya
tanzania mozambique
madagascar northern madagascar etc you
will see very significant and very deep
indian influences
you will see it in the kind of clothing
the people there wear it's very similar
to the kind of textiles you had in
gujarat in the past 500 years
the kind of dresses women wear very
colorful bright dresses with these
interesting patterns which are almost
the same as the kind of textiles you add
in gujarat traditionally
if you see the cuisine
you see the indian spice is a very
significant
you you see the use of indian spices in
much the same way indians use the spices
you see turmeric you see clove you see
ginger you see
other indian spices peppers nutmeg and
other spices which are very much used in
eastern african cuisine i think eastern
african cuisine tastes very much like
indian cuisine
and many other things the people of
eastern africa especially in somalia
ethiopia etc they look very much indian
in some way so there if i'm not sure if
any genetic studies have been done but
there is certainly
indian genetics at play in there
so i think india conquered eastern
africa culturally more than militarily
the same whether india conquered china
and japan and korea
culturally
not militarily
india has never indulged in colonialism
you had the cholas of course who
conquered southeast asia but again it
was not colonialism it was
there was more cultural
export than any kind of import into
india so that's how india has always
been as a civilization as a culture
if we do conquer we don't plunder we
don't massacre and we don't extract
we actually give something
more than we take so i think the same
thing happened in austria in in africa
for
several thousand years at least four
thousand years because there is evidence
of indian presence in africa that goes
back at least four thousand years and
the presence
is found in the form
of indian cattle breeds the zebu cattle
which are native to india
are found enough in africa
and they have been found there enough in
africa for at least four thousand years
and there are other other data points as
well so i think india has been present
in africa especially eastern africa for
at least four thousand years indians
have been present there
but was there a military conquest i
don't know we
don't have evidence as of
today okay let's see some more questions
tabla vibes says can you tell us about
all the blunders done by sri naruji and
his family
be taking the issue of kashmir to the un
covering up nitaj's contribution or
others
you know i i think i will make a
separate video about this because i may
not remember everything right now there
is so much to be covered i think there's
an interesting book that i can refer to
let me give you the book reference
there is
yes let me share this i think this book
will
uh
give you all the details
one second so this is a good book
so this is a book by mr rajnikanth
puranik it is from 2016. it's called
nehru's 97 major blunders
it's a very good book i have it it's not
here it's somewhere else uh
it's a very good book it's a very
detailed book in which he goes into
detail with about 97
major blunders that the towering
personality shri jawaharlal nehru did
as the prime minister of india it's only
about him it's not about his descendants
it's only about
mr nehru himself and his role in shaping
the india of today
and as you can see it's a very
well review rated book 4.5 out of 5 is
excellent
so i would recommend this book highly
it's a very good it's a very well
researched book about this topic so i
will say only that for now
if you can buy this book buy it
and you will get lots of details
about this topic
okay some more questions
hersh says what was so special about
africa that all the human species
originated there and not in any other
part of the world
we don't know
evolution
is often spontaneous it's often random
it's often a matter of chance or luck
that certain species emerge from certain
regions
and thus far the
true origins of humanity are still murky
the best evidence that we have indicates
that humanity originated in africa
but we are also finding more and more
evidence of a significant
amount of very ancient archaic human
presence
in asia and also in parts of europe
eurasia now some of these ancient
fossils have been
have been interpreted as primate fossils
that is fossils of apes or monkey
monkeys
but what is the dividing line between an
ancient monkey
and an ancient hominid
it's often a matter of interpretation
and then there are these very strange
very strange
data points like there is evidence of
human-like footprints
that are several million years old in
eurasia i think i don't remember exactly
where it was i think it's somewhere in
europe i think
and that predates the earliest evidence
of humans in africa
so as of today i think we should hold
our judgment
more data is emerging more discoveries
are coming out
the story of humanity is yet to be fully
told we don't know for sure
that humanity originated in africa the
best evidence thus far the best
unambiguous evidence thus far
indicates that humanity most likely
emerged in africa
and yet if we find more evidence the
story will change that is how it works
in science
nothing is set in stone you can't say i
believe there's an in the end of story
when new evidence comes in the story
changes because you have new data
and it may refute your old beliefs or
what you had assumed to be true before
that
so i think the story of humanity
humanity is very complex it's not a
linear story there have been several
branches of the human family tree we are
the surviving branch but even our origin
story is not linear we have
contributions genetic contributions from
neanderthals from denisovans
and maybe other
ancient hominid species that we don't
even know of as of today
so it's a very complex
origin story and it's not yet
uh completely known
so maybe we emerged somewhere else also
that is also
a possibility that has to be taken
seriously
okay some more questions
chandelier manmek sharma says can you
advise authentic book on the life of sri
chingish khan i think there's a number
of books my research has been done
outside of books
i have read lots of journal articles
and accounts of various historians
outside of books not books but if you
want
a good book i think there's a book by
jack weatherford okay let me let me
go to amazon and let's let's google it
and let me recommend a couple of books
so
yes this book is good gringiskan in the
making of the modern world by jack
weatherford i haven't read it myself but
it is very
well rated so i am assuming it must be
good i haven't read this book myself
there is this book by john mann also
which seems to be good i haven't read
this book either
but yeah i would say that i would i
would i would recommend these two books
one is
the book by jack weatherford and
then the book by john mann purely on the
basis of the good reviews it has got i
haven't read these books myself my
research has been done in a completely
different way i have been researching
genghis khan since the late 1990s
through lots of various journal articles
national geographic articles and god
knows what else all kinds of clippings
and all that so it's a lot of
data points that i have accumulated in
my
throughout the course of my research
that come from a lot of different
sources
so that's how i learned about drinkish
khan and that's why my interpretation
and my understanding of chinese khan is
so different from that of your
mainstream historians but if you want to
if you want a couple of books to
understand this man that's a great man
then i would
i would recommend those two books
okay let's take some more questions
samantha says you said in ranveer allah
showed that india's independence in 1947
wasn't abstract
what do you mean by that
are we living on a parallel earth and
what's your belief on this i think these
are two different questions
i don't remember exactly what i said in
ranvi's show i think i said that
i have said that on this channel as well
i didn't say it was abstract i said that
india's independence in 1947 was an
illusion
what happened in 1947
was to put it crudely
it was a transfer of power from one set
of crooks
to another set of crooks there was
nothing democratic about it power was
given to india
india was given freedom on the terms of
the british
we did not get freedom on our own terms
they gave it to us on their terms and
that's why their system continues even
today
the laws the british wrote are still in
force in india today the institutions
the british created are still ruling
over us today
power was handed to the congress party
it was not a democratic transfer of
power
they decided they chose the congress
party to give power to
and they chose to partition the country
and they hand picked jawaharlal nehru as
the prime minister of india he was
selected as a prime minister he was not
elected in an election the first
election was in the 1950s i think
so it was a transfer of power
and india became a dominion or something
of the of the uk i don't even know what
is the real status today
so it was india is still deeply deeply
deeply colonized in all ways we are even
more colonized today than we were in
1947. so that's why i said that india's
independence in 1947 was an illusion it
was a sham we are still not
independent we are still completely
colonized all our institutions are
colonial
our
parliamentary system is colonial
we have prime ministers
who are chosen by
mps we don't get to elect a prime
minister we can only elect an mp
and all these mps get together to choose
a prime minister or a chief minister and
you see what happens as a result of that
today we have a good prime minister one
of the strongest prime ministers we have
had since 1947
but see the other prime minister with
the prime ministers we have had before
that and see the kind of horse trading
that happens in elections or after
elections
and what kind of chief ministers come up
in certain parts of the country in
certain periods of time
so our
democracy
is an illusory democracy we don't really
have the power to choose to select our
own leaders
they are selected only indirectly and so
many things more we are completely
colonized even today so that's what i
meant by saying that our independence
was an illusion
now the other question is are we living
on a parallel earth
i i don't know
i haven't seen two earths so i only know
one earth so that's all i know that's
the best
date
from the best observational evidence
that we have
only one earth exists only one solar
system exists
only one universe exists if there are
parallel universes or parallel earths
well it's
something we can only speculate about
we haven't actually observed it science
is about observational evidence and
physical
phenomena so from the physical phenomena
that we observe and from the
observational evidence that we have
there is only one earth that we can see
so that's all i can tell you that's all
i can report to you from the
observations i have made
okay some more questions
okay lots of hands
okay why doesn't india try to expand its
borders like china or any other country
please take my question hi hi
okay
well india has never been an
expansionist nation
or culture or civilization
even during the most
apart from the cholas we have never
truly been
expansionist i think even the questions
kanesha etc
they did expand india's sphere of
influence in india's territories
all the way up to the
caspian and naral seas and all the way
into xinjiang etc but apart from these
two three episodes
or chapters of india's history we have
not really been an expansionist people
there have been migrations out of india
that conquered all of europe etc that's
a different story
but overall our culture is a very
peaceful
accommodative culture
and
expansion also is predicated upon
military strength
and
it's also predicated on political
continuity and unity in the country
today's
political system in india is very
fragmented this so-called federal system
of india
it weakens india it pulls india in 50
different directions
every state acts like a separate country
they have their own rules they have
their own way of dealing with things
they are often
working against the central government
especially if it's a different political
party
and there are elections every year in
some part of the country
and even at the central level
if the election throws up a new party
then the policies change overnight
and what was happening may be completely
reversed
for example when you had morality desire
come in he destroyed india's
intelligence network in pakistan
and the same thing was done by
ipk gujarat so this sort of system is
extraordinarily unstable
it is extraordinarily detrimental to
india's national interest so our
political system is designed
to keep india unstable and weak so that
is one reason why india is weak
and secondly india has simply not
managed to bring its economy up it's
it's growing of course but it's not
growing fast enough we want double digit
growth every year for the next 20 years
only then can india
quickly
become a middle income country
but that will take a lot of doing as of
today india is again after the pandemic
it's picking up growth slowly
it's a good sign i'm very happy to see
that but it needs to go much further
and
again with
economic growth we need proportional
military growth as well we need to
invest in the military because what's
the point of having a strong economy and
having a rich country if you can't
defend it
so if these things are put in place then
we can expand our borders and reclaim
the lands we have lost
those are justifiable
aspirations
we have lost lands that have been ours
for 10 000 years or more
it is justifiable
to seek those lands back
of course powers like china will not
want that to happen but it's curious
that they won't akhand china but they
are against akanda bharat so india needs
to strengthen itself
and then deal with china properly
man to man
we will support your account china
project if you will support our
khandabad project or something like that
so that's why india as of today is not
trying to expand its borders because
it's not strong enough
it's not strong enough politically
there's no political continuity there's
a lot of
forces pulling india in different
directions
there are so many
outside forces at work in india
undermining india's culture and
undermining india's politics
and so on so these are the factors that
keep india weak and unstable
and unless india becomes strong
and stable it will never be able to
achieve
any objective of reclaiming lost
territories
so that's that's why it is so
okay let's take a couple of more
questions
mr tomcat says why did pakistan help
taliban in conquering panjushir
will india lost kashmir if taliban plus
pakistan with china covert attack india
the recent
news is that there is a rift between
taliban leaders please share your views
well the pakistanis want to maintain
some sort of leverage
over the taliban
what's happened in the past month is
that the taliban have been able to run
over the country and capture the entire
country and take it under their control
without any pakistani help the americans
gave the country to them on a platter
so that's why only the the punjabi
valley region was left out where you had
this uh
alliance of what's his name
who were holding out
so to in order to
re restore some sort of some form of
leverage over the taliban the pakistanis
sent in their isi chief and they did
some
aerial
activity with helicopters i think
to try and disclose dislodge the
the resistance from the punjabi valley
so pakistan wants to ensure that it has
some continued leverage over the taliban
leadership
that's why they are trying to stay
involved in some way or the other
now your other question is will india
lose kashmir if taliban plus pakistan
plus china get involved and attack india
look
the taliban
is not a significant force
they have been terrorists for the past
20 years they are not a proper military
force they are a ragtag bunch of
terrorists
the only reason they have afghanistan
today is because the americans gave
afghanistan to them
they don't have a strong military they
are no match
for the indian armed forces
if india desires india can take over
afghanistan in a month's time if india
so desires
of course then you will have the
involvement of china and pakistan and
whatnot it will become a mess
many multiple actors will get involved
but the indian armed forces are way way
way more powerful than anything the
taliban has or anything even the
pakistanis have the only powerful force
that india has to contend with is china
i don't think the chinese will
as of today want any
mess in kashmir
because that is going to create
spillover into china as well
because once india knows the chinese
have been doing this there will be
repercussions for the chinese as well
so i don't think any
i don't foresee
any problems in kashmir in the
foreseeable future
i don't think the taliban have any
appetite for getting involved anywhere
right now
in the next few years they want to
consolidate their whole over the country
and that's what they're going to be
working towards they will try and
balance pakistan and china and iran and
maybe the uss also
against each other play one against the
other
and that that's how they will try and
continue
ruling over afghanistan as of today the
americans want the taliban to rule
afghanistan maybe they want the chinese
to get involved right now and the
pakistan is to get involved right now
and maybe four or five years down the
line it will come back to bite the
chinese in the pakistanis maybe that's
the plan see the geopolitical game is a
long term game
right now you're seeing all kinds of
things happening in afghanistan
just
calm down and watch it let it happen
the real game is over the next five or
ten years right now the pakistanis are
getting involved and this and that it's
okay let it happen it doesn't make it it
doesn't really matter in the long term
in the long term what matters
is
what is the long term fate
of the taliban leadership
and of the chinese involvement and of
pakistan that is the real big game
okay
more questions
this is an interesting question by
sirohe my opinion about mega cities like
dubai being built by modern day slaves
from india
so you know in the 1960s and 70s dubai
was a fishing village there was nothing
there
then somehow
then somehow the way became rich
i think dubai doesn't have much oil
unlike the other gulf states
but somehow
money began flowing into dubai
some of it was from india
through certain
through certain channels i would say
and then that money
was used to start building this city
and it was indian labor that built these
big cities like dubai abu dhabi etc
people from the from the
from kerala etc would go to work in the
gulf and they would send the money back
to india
so they would be treated like slaves
almost like very cheap disposable labor
in the entire cities like dubai abu
dhabi etc were built with this cheap
disposable
indian labor
the pakistan is also there bangladesh is
also etc nepalese
afghans to some extent and people from
the philippines so these are the
disposable labor in the gulf region
today i think there are fewer indians
working in the gulf
and today india has a very strong
political and geopolitical relationship
with the gulf nations like dubai abu
dhabi qatar uae and all that
so today the perception about india
seems to have changed
to some extent in the gulf
and today
i think there will be fewer indians
working as de facto slaves there but i'm
sure there are still many indians who
work there
i think it's it's it's terrible
it's a consequence of india's very
very
paltry per capita gdp which means that
most people
live in poverty that's why they have to
go far away to work as slaves in order
to send the money back to the families
that i will suffer but my family will
have a better life that sort of
sentiment
it's all because of this the policies of
the nehru and regime and the subsequent
regimes which kept india poor these were
povertarian
policies
mr mohandas gandhi had a povertarian
vision for india he wanted indians to to
weave
khadi
every day
and earned just barely enough to stay
alive that was mr gandhi's vision for
india and that's what mr nehru
implemented
today india is a very different country
india is industrializing i hope it
industrializes more india needs to move
away from services
and more into manufacturing
because that is what truly
industrializes the country
otherwise we run the risk of becoming
cyber coolies just like indian slave
labor built up dubai and abu dhabi and
these beautiful cities in the middle
east today indian slave labor or cheap
labor will build up these virtual
monopolies google facebook and whatnot
it's the same pattern happening again
so india needs to move away from
offering its services and its
intellectual
labor
for cheap and indian is to start
investing in its own
uh in its own infrastructure
that's what needs to happen so that is
the lesson we can learn
from the fact that dubai and abu dhabi
and these cities were built so cheaply
with indian labor
it happened it's it's terrible it
happened but there is a lesson to be
learned from that and that lesson is
valid even today in the digital age
okay i will take one more question
why have you used a relief map in your
thumbnail
well i felt like using a relief map is
it bad
do you have an objection to that
i think it's a good map don't you think
so
okay one more question a real question
ayush says asks the reason behind the
decline of the indus valley civilization
it was not a separate civilization it
was one of the phases of india's 10 000
plus year old civilization
the decline happened over 2000 years
because of climate change the indian
monsoon used to be very intense it fed
this enormous river called the saraswati
which declined over many thousand years
eventually there was not enough water in
the river it dried out
the other rivers continued but they also
declined and therefore the lifestyle
that was there in that river valley
region in the sindhu region
was no longer sustainable because many
rivers dried out and the entire climate
overall was much drier
became much drier and therefore the
people of this region over the centuries
over 2000 years they moved to other
parts of india where they still they
were their descendants still live today
so it was not the decline it was just
the moving away from that region to
other parts of india or maybe even other
places of the world
because during the indus valley
time
during the harappan phase
of india's civilization we find indian
genetics in australia
we find indian genetics
going throughout europe and so on so
it's a very complex scenario but the if
you want in one sentence they declare
why did this
this
region decline it's because of climate
change because of
the monsoon declining significantly over
a number of thousands of years that's
what happened
okay okay let's see
shall i take one more question
chandelier
okay okay this is going to be the last
question for today do you think india
gets any benefit in exchange
for helping bangladesh in their freedom
struggle
i see india just got an influx of
bangladeshis
i think it was a
it was a
great potential opportunity for india
i mean
from 1947 to 1971 that's how many years
24 years
so that part of bengal had been
a separate country for only 24 years
india should have either reintegrated
east bengal or bangladesh into india
because we conquered it militarily fair
and square
or india should have ensured that
a
pro-india government was installed there
and india should have ensured the
continuity of such a pro-india
government in bangladesh india did
neither of these things
india allowed bangladesh to just run
amok and go into its own direction and
there have been times when bangladeshi
governments have been very strongly anti
india today
if you look at the common bangladeshi
person they are very much anti india
they are very much pro pakistan
their textbooks teach them that they
want independence on their own through
their so-called mukti bahini movement
which is absolute nonsense
the mukti bahini was a rag tag guerrilla
outfit
they could do nothing to prevent the
wholesale massacre of more than five
million bangladeshis at the end of the
punjabi army what did the mukhi bani do
it could do nothing it was trained by
india and when india discovered that the
muktibaini is no match for the
pakistanis that's when india had to
intervene militarily it was india that
freed bangladesh from the pakistanis but
today the bangladesh are taught that
they want independence on their own
india just came to take photographs
that's sort of nonsense
and after independence bangladesh was
allowed to go its own way it became an
independent country i don't know why
because today you have millions of
bangladeshis in india all across india
from north south east west everywhere
these illegal bangladeshi immigrants
assam's entire demographics have changed
the great sacrifices of the ohan dynasty
of lalith
of
of lachit borphukan
who prevented the mobilization and the
turkification of assam all of that has
been undone
by the policies of the neruvian and
subsequent regimes
right
the border with bangladesh is almost
open it seems they can just walk in any
time they want
so i think india got no benefit
from
1971 if you look at the long-term
perspective
what did india gain from that yeah the
only benefit was that pakistan was was
broken into that's the only benefit
but apart from that there's no other
benefit and today here bangladesh has
millions of them millions of them all
across india illegal immigrants who have
valid papers other cards and pan cards
and whatnot it's a horrific situation
it's never going to be reversed
they have the documentation that that
proves that they are indian citizens so
what's india going to be able to do
about them absolutely nothing the only
long-term solution is to re-absorb
bangladesh and then to
deal with it in uh
in a manner that is
that is best for india's natural
interest
what that what prop what is to be done
to deal with them that remains to be
seen but that is for the leadership to
determine
so that is in brief about this question
i think i will stop here now thank you
so much for all your questions
it's great to see you all next week i'm
going to do two sessions
and there will be some changes next week
in the kind of session that i do so i
will let you know in a couple of days
until then
thank you so much for your viewership
thank you for
all your participation
and i will see you next week very soon
take care
have a good day and have a good night
bye bye